Image Viewer
Always wondered a way to view photos together with sighted people, but you can't do it because you're blind? Well, you can't look at the photo and determine by yourself what you can see there, but this simple yet cool software is written especially to try to fill this gap.
Let's say that it could be quite nice alternative to Windows Photo Viewer, just with additional features for blind in mind.

How to use?
When you open the program, you're presented with empty window. This is for showing the actual images for sighted people.
Then, you have the menu bar. As some things may be self explanatory, still I would like to talk about some of them:
File menu is really clear, in which you can open the directory of images, or use CTRL +O for doing it quicker.
When you open the directory, program will list you all suported images found inside it. You can switch images by pressing right or left arrows (for going forward or backward).
Images can be in jpg or png format.
Image Viewer, if you set the file associations during installation, can also open files directly from Windows explorer. Still, you will be able to navigate between another images found in the directory.
Now let's talk about "commands" menu:
In this menu, along with standart "next/previous image" things you will get very cool features:
- Get description:
Probably the most cool feature packed here.
With this, you can retrieve description about opened image. It works not only like standart OCR for recognising text, but can as well give you information about what's happening in the picture, as well as determine the objects and even ages of people.
Information is retrieved wia Cloud Vision API. This is an online service, so internet connection is required.
Note: this is available only for screen reader users as nothing is presented to the screen.
If you want to keep the result somewhere, you can copy the description by accessing "copy image description" from menu bar, or just pressing f5.
- write long description:
Let's say that someone described this photo for you or you just know what it is and you would like to remember it.
No problem! With Image Viewer this is possible.
You can assign your own description to an image. Just click on the menu, or press Control +F2, write into edit field, save it and you're done. Now everytime you'll be on the image, you can press F3 and hear your own text. Furthermore, in options, you can choose whether it has to be read automatically or not.
- Rename:
Have you ever tried to compare your photos and your music collection and asked yourself: why your music files mostly have tidy and logical names like artist-title.mp3, but photo file names are only the bunch of digits without any sense?
Now you can fix that!
In the Image Viewer, you'll have an option to rename a file. The name is formed from two fields: TimestampTXT-short description. Timestamp is the text taken from a file tag, the date and time when the picture was taken, as almost all cameras nowadays write some information. However in some pictures it can be missing, then file time is used. Short description will be your additional text which you want to add to a file name, such as location where the photo was taken or anything else.
- Slide show:
For blind this feature is really unrequired.
But it was added for sighted people to enjoy.
What it does actually is just switching the images automatically once 3 seconds so you don't need to press right arrow everytime.

Hotkeys:
CTRL +O: Open folder with images
CTRL +S: enable or disable slide show
right arrow: next image
left arrow: previous image
F2: rename the file
CTRL +F2: write your own description to the image file
F3: say file description
F4: retrieve description of image using Cloud Vision service
F5: copy previously retrieved description of image

Copyright (C) 2020-2022 Hermis Kasperavičius
E-mail: hermis.kasperavicius@gmail.com
If you have comments, suggestions or bug reports, or just want to say something, feel free to contact me!
